All right,
it's 10.30,
so we'll get started.
Good to see everyone.
No new announcements really,
other than that homework two is
due tomorrow and don't forget to
look at solutions to past labs
and homeworks.
You're kind of already asked to
review the solutions to previous
homeworks as part of the first
question on a new homework,
right? Like the first question
on homework two tells you to go
and look at the homework one
solutions which you can find if
you just click the homework one
link on the course website so do
that but then also make sure to
look at the solutions to lab
exercises especially for
activities you didn't get a
chance to go through in
yesterday's lab but also for
ones where you want a little
more clarification I said this
earlier but when it comes time
to studying for midterms which
you know our first midterm is
not that far away it's on
October 6th students often
neglect looking at labs I think
homework is the most important
thing, and homework is
important, yes, but the content
in labs is just as important.
So make sure to regularly review
those solutions as well.
The plan for today is to recap
something I introduced very
briefly at the end of Tuesday's
class, which was this idea of a
linear combination of vectors.
This is something you played
around with in yesterday's lab.
And then we will further explore
something else you looked at in
yesterday's lab, which is this
operation called the dot product
between two vectors.
Okay, so let me start by
reintroducing the two example
vectors we left off with on
Tuesday I said I have a vector u
3 1 and a vector v 4 negative 6
because I'm gonna remind me
notationally like what would I
Like what set would I say these
vectors belong to?
Yeah, I I wouldn't call it
squared I would call it r2,
but I think you have the right
symbol in mind.
I would say u and v
Are both in r2
Why well it's because they both
have two Numbers in them, right?
Does that mean the length of
each of these is two?
No, remember the length has a
precise definition It's the
square root of the sum of the
squares of the components So the
length of u is the square root
of 9 plus 1, which is the square
root of 10.
And the length of v is the
square root of 4 squared plus
negative 6 squared, which I
think is the square root of 52.
Those are their lengths.
So what were the two operations
we looked at on Tuesday?
I said vectors out of the box.
There are two things you can do
with them,
other than find their length.
There were two operations we
looked at.
Yeah? Scalar multiplication and
addition.
Good.
The first was that we could add
two vectors.
And so for example,
that tells us that u plus v
is a valid operation,
and it returns the same vector
as v plus u, because this
operation is commutative.
And we saw on Tuesday how to
visualize this addition.
And we can do that by drawing
either
vector as an arrow starting at
the origin.
Here I've drawn u because I'm
going three units to the right
and one unit up.
And then I draw v
starting at the tip
of u.
And the result I get when I
connect them
is that sum u plus v.
Okay?
And if I started with v at the
origin and then to that tacked
on u,
I would get v plus u, but it
would be the same vector.
Okay?
So that was the first operation
we looked at, and then the
second operation we looked at
was that of scalar
multiplication,
in which I said if this is the
vector u,
well then multiplying u by a
scalar,
which it stretches or compresses
u,
but preserves its general
direction.
So for example,
if that's u,
then this is a half of u.
And this is,
it's not perfectly drawn to
scale, but something like that
is negative 2 times u.
Double the length points in the
opposite direction.
And what property did we say
that all of the scalar multiples
of a given vector obey? Like,
what is true of u, a half of u,
negative 2 u's, 17 u's? What is
true of all of those vectors
together?
What's that one? Collinear?
They are collinear, that is
true,
but there's something related to
that that I mentioned on
Tuesday.
They're parallel?
They are parallel.
Well,
it's related to that as well.
Yeah.
They're all on the same line.
Yeah, they all live on the same
line.
These are all just various ways
of stating the properties that
we just heard.
They all live on the same line.
And equivalently,
any line through the origin you
think of can be expressed as the
set of scalar multiples of one
vector.
OK, and that's the kind of thing
we're going to talk about next
week.
Why must it be through the
origin? Well,
one of the scalar multiples of
any vector is 0 times a vector.
That would give me the vector 0,
0 if I'm dealing with vectors in
R2.
So that means if I'm considering
the set of all scalar multiples
of u,
the 0 vector, as we call it,
would have to be included.
This is an idea we will see a
bit more soon.
Soon.
Back to these two vectors,
u and v.
Good notes is acting up again.
Whatever.
We can write them out.
The last expression I wrote up
on the board on Tuesday
was one that looked like this,
3u minus 1 half v.
This is what I called a linear
combination of u and v.
And the way to think of a linear
combination is as I've taken a
little bit of one vector plus a
little bit of another vector.
And here I'm just starting with
two vectors, u and v,
but I could have had a u, v, w,
x, y, and z,
and take a linear combination of
all of those.
And so an expression that looks
like 2u plus 3v minus 17x
plus
354y, that is a linear
combination of those vectors u,
v, x, and y.
And so you should think of a
linear combination as a new
vector I'm making by taking
various amounts of my original
vectors.
I like to think of these
original vectors, in this case,
in 3u minus a half v.
I like to think of those as
being my building blocks.
And my linear combination is
saying,
well, how much of each building
block do I want to take to
produce this new vector?
So 3u minus a half of v.
Sure, we could work this out
algebraically.
That's not the interesting part,
but we can do that.
What is this going to give me?
What is 3u?
Yeah,
Allison.
9, 3.
Good.
And to that, I'm going to add
negative 1 half of v.
So what vector should I add this
to?
Yeah.
Negative 2 and 3.
So I should land at 7, 6.
So what this is saying is that
you can make the vector 7,
6 using u and v as you're
building blocks.
So think of this as a vector
that is possible to reach
using u and v.
And how do we visualize that?
This is a picture I showed you
briefly on Tuesday.
Here I've drawn u and v in
orange and blue.
Then I've shown you 3v and
negative 1 half,
sorry, 3u and negative 1 half v.
But because what What I'm trying
to do here is visualize the
addition of 3u and negative 1
half v.
I've drawn negative 1 half v,
not at the origin, but at the
end of 3u.
So what this is showing me is
how to create my new vector,
3u minus a half of v,
by traveling in the direction of
u as much as I want,
and then in the direction of v.
Okay?
So if I wanted to build another
linear combination of u and v,
what we're seeing is that it
would involve traveling some
amount along this line,
that is some amount of u,
like maybe this is for u,
this is negative 1 2 u,
whatever amount I want there,
and then whatever amount I want
in the v direction.
So I can go in the negative v
direction,
I can go in the positive v
all of those would be OK.
All right? So a question for you
is,
what would the vector
negative 2u
plus 3v look like?
What I want you to do is take
30 seconds and see if you can
just draw
the u and v that are currently
on my screen right now,
and sort of guesstimate where
negative 2u plus 3v would end
up.
Maybe as a hint, I'll put this
picture up here.
Okay,
can someone help me out? Where
is negative 2u plus 3v going to
live?
How would I figure that out?
Again, I intentionally didn't
write the numbers out for u and
v here, because I want us to do
this visually.
And then we can do the
arithmetic and verify that we
did it correctly.
Well,
you would put u in the opposite
direction,
and you would double the length.
Good.
So this, if this is u going up
and to the right,
negative 2u is going to travel
down and to the left,
double the length.
So this is going to be negative
2u.
You know what, instead of
putting that orange, because
it's going to make it confusing,
let's make it purple.
Negative 2u,
great.
Then what do we have?
Yeah, go for it.
You would do v times 3,
like multiply it by the length
of 3.
Exactly, what I'm going to do is
I'm going to take this vector v,
triple its length, so it's
probably going to go past my
iPad.
But instead of drawing it there,
I'm going to draw it over here.
And so I'm going to have, oops,
I'll draw it dotted here.
And so my result is going to
look something like this.
Minus 2u plus 3v.
Okay, and to verify that that
works out algebraically,
remember u was 3, 1 and v was 4,
negative 6.
So the first component should be
negative 6 plus 12.
And the second component should
be negative 2 minus 18.
That looks like 6,
negative 20.
Seems about right.
Maybe I did the algebra a little
wrong, but yeah.
I just have a question.
So earlier,
for the 3u minus 1 half v
example,
you said that you could have put
the v after going that way or
going down that way.
What I was more describing is
it's OK.
Let me take a step back here.
To create 3u minus 1 half v,
there are no choices.
It tells us exactly how many u's
and exactly how many v's to
make.
I guess what I was alluding to
is if I change this number,
it would,
like if I change 3 to something
else,
it's the same process.
So when it is like minus or it's
a negative scalar? You always
flip the direction.
Yeah,
correct, correct,
correct.
So do we see here how the vector
6,
negative 20 has been produced as
a linear combination of u and v?
Yeah?
Now,
these two examples in which I've
told you what amounts to
multiply u and v by,
that's the easy way.
Or that's the easy direction of
thinking of a linear
combination.
It's like saying,
make a LEGO using three of the
first kind of block and two of
the second block.
That's OK.
You can do that.
The harder question is,
what if I just tell you what to
make,
but don't tell you how to make
it?
So what if I instead say,
go and make the vector 7,
negative 27? That was just a
random example.
Or I just tell you some vector
to make,
and I say,
can you make it using u and v?
That's a more complicated
problem.
And that's the kind of problem
I want us to think about here.
And so we're going to work on an
activity.
I'm going to say, suppose we
have two vectors, but instead of
them being in R2,
I'm going to put them in R3.
Let's suppose we have the
vectors x,
which is 3, negative 1, and 2,
y, which is 1,
4, and 3.
And what I want you to do is
write the vector
z,
which is 9, negative 16,
negative 1, as a linear
combination
of x and y.
In other words, what I'm saying
is fill in the blanks.
9, negative 16, negative 1
equals something
times x
plus something times y.
And what I want you to do is
find the x's and y's.
And there were some activities
similar to this in yesterday's
lab,
but it's important that we talk
about this here.
Before you do the algebra,
what I want to convince you of
is that there isn't necessarily
an answer.
It's possible that you try and
do this,
And we end up finding you just
can't do it.
Let me give you an example
physically.
Since we're thinking with
vectors in R3,
we can imagine them as like
arrows in this room here.
And what if I tell you,
make this vector?
Pretend it's a vector 1, 2, 3.
Pretend that was z.
And pretend x just traveled that
direction on the floor,
and y traveled that direction on
the floor.
then no amount of x and y is
going to reach up here.
They're stuck on the floor.
Do you agree with that?
So it's possible the answer is
you can't do it.
But maybe you can do it.
Because what if x was just this
way on the floor,
y was just that way on the
floor,
and z was also just another
vector on the floor that was
diagonal?
Then you could make it.
So maybe the answer is you can
do it.
Maybe the answer is you can't.
But in this case, I want to see
if you can try and figure out a
way to make this happen.
A does resolve to an
integer.
It's because I put b equal to 3,
it is 3 and subtracted,
and that's what I did before.
This is random.
Did anyone else sign up for that
email about skills at the Big
House today?
Maybe they only sent it to
people who work here, but there
was this random email that went
out a few months ago that was
like,
today they have a skills
training boot camp on the field
at the Big House.
So I'm going to that and you can
kick field goals and stuff.
Every question feels different.
We will execute any of the
practice.
And that's part of the college
for the mayor.
So technically,
if they operate the college,
Give you another minute to start
writing out some initial
thoughts.
This would be like maybe one
question.
OK.
How did you start to find
numbers to put in these blanks?
Remember, my task for you was
try and make the vector 9,
negative 16, negative 1 using
the building blocks x and y.
Yeah, tell me how you set that
up.
I could, like,
use A and B to do scalar
multiples.
Sure.
So that's a good first step.
We should think of variables to
represent
the amounts of x and y.
I'm going to use C and D because
I'm going to bring in a picture
that uses those numbers.
But yeah, I could have been A
and B.
It's fine.
OK?
And then each component of x
would be multiplied by C.
Good.
And y would be multiplied by d,
so an example would be like 3c
plus d equals 1.
Good, all I've done here is I've
substituted in x and y.
And now, indeed,
right here,
it doesn't look like the systems
of equations you've seen before,
but it is just a system of
equations in terms of the
variables c and d.
The first one is saying, the
first line is saying 9 is equal
to 3C plus D.
The second is saying negative 16
is equal to negative C plus 4D.
And the third is saying negative
1 is equal to 2C plus 3D.
Okay?
Are we comfortable on how we
arrived here?
Alright.
So just to save a little bit of
time,
is the kind of thing you'll
practice in homework and in lab,
there is a solution in this
case.
What is the solution?
Anyone find it?
Okay.
C is equal to four.
Good.
There is a solution,
and it's a unique solution.
This is the only combination of
C and D that work here.
So what this is saying is 4x
minus 3y
equals z.
That is,
z is a linear combination of x
and y.
But if these equations were such
that there were no solution,
then there would be no way to
make z using x and y,
OK?
Now, there's two perspectives I
want to show you of this
picture.
The first is going to require us
to switch over to the notes
here.
These are different, what are
about to appear are different
vectors,
but you get the idea.
Like there's a point I'm trying
to make here.
Here it says W and R,
pretend this just says X and Y.
And what I've drawn in 3D is
several of their linear
combinations in gray.
So for example, this long one
down here is negative 0.75W
minus 3R.
And these other ones in the top
right in gray are just other
linear combinations of W and R.
And if you look at this picture,
especially if you hit this
toggle plane button,
you'll say, OK, well, whatever.
These are R and W,
or in our example case, X and Y,
are just vectors in R3.
They're linear combinations or
just other vectors in R3,
nothing special.
But what you should notice is
that all of the linear
combinations of W and R here,
what is true about them?
What is this picture trying to
illustrate?
Got it.
They all lie in the same plane.
Yeah, they're all trapped in
this two-dimensional slice of
3D.
So if I didn't draw this plane,
it would look like, okay,
R and W just live in 3D and so
do all of their linear
combinations, but there's no
real pattern to them.
But then if you look at it this
way, it's like, wait,
it seems like there's a slice
they all live on.
That slice is called a plane,
and anything that you can make
with R and W is forced to live
on this plane.
Can't escape it.
This is analogous to that
example I gave you just a few
moments ago,
where I said pretend x was a
vector that just lived that way
on the classroom floor and y was
a vector that lived that way on
the classroom floor.
Anything you can make with x and
y is just trapped to the
classroom floor.
I can't suddenly levitate
because I didn't give it the
components to be able to do
that.
Similarly, with this R and W,
anything you can make with them
is trapped to be on this plane.
So if I give you a third vector
who lives on this plane,
that is, if I drew it as an
arrow from the origin,
it entirely would live on this
plane.
Then I could make it with R and
W.
But if I gave you some other
vector that's not on this plane,
well, then you couldn't make it.
You see what I mean by that?
So R and W, in this example,
the linear combinations of them
are restricted to this plane,
OK?
And what we will see, and I will
emphasize this more next week,
if you take any two vectors in
R3,
as long as they don't point in
the same direction,
then the set of their linear
combinations is a plane.
So any two vectors in R3 that
don't point in the same
direction,
we say they uniquely define a
plane.
Okay, and simply so not only are
all the linear combinations of X
and Y on this plane, but also
the reverse is true.
Anything on this plane is a
linear combination of R and W.
So I could pick any vector that
lives on this plane and there is
a way to make it with R and W.
But anything not on this plane
you can't do it.
Okay,
and so how is this related to
the example we were just working
with,
the connection
is that this vector z was on the
plane that
x and y define.
If I drew a new picture with
just x and y on it in R3
and filled in the plane that
contains both of them, then this
z-vector also was on that plane,
because I was able to make that
z-vector using x and y.
But if I wasn't able to make
that z-vector,
well, then it wasn't on the
plane containing x and y.
That's a key idea.
any two vectors in
R3 that
aren't
scalar multiples of each other.
uniquely define a plane, okay?
So again, the analogy to this
example I had you work on is
that x and y uniquely define a
plane.
Any linear combination of x and
y live on that plane
because z is a linear
combination of x and y,
it also lives on that plane.
Paul?
Does uniquely here mean no other
two vectors could create the
same plane?
No, it means there's no other
amount of x and y
that you could take that also
equals z.
So let's come back here.
What I'm getting at here,
uniquely,
is that 4x minus 3y equals z,
but there's no other linear
combination of x and y that also
equals z.
Oh.
But we may end up in a situation
where it could be the case that
10x plus 5y also equals z.
That wouldn't be true here, but
you'll see as we introduce more
building block vectors, like we
had another vector z and another
vector w,
that could end up being the
case.
So in that case, would it not be
unique anymore, because there's
two different? Because there
could be two or more ways of
making the same output given our
inputs.
But here if you think of X and Y
as the input vectors and Z is
the output There's only one way
to combine the inputs to get to
the output.
That's what I mean by unique.
Yeah, good clarification.
Yeah
You mean the vectors themselves
or the constants the car yeah
the constants are unique Yeah,
how do you determine that?
Just in this case because when
we solve this system of
equations, there was only one
Correct.
Yeah,
that's what I'm about to show
you.
So I'll say no other C and D
satisfy these equations.
So that's one perspective I
wanted to show you, that two
vectors in R3 define a plane,
and any other vector that's on
that plane can be made as a
linear combination of your
original two.
The other perspective is leaning
more into the system of
equations that we've looked at.
And if we copy these three,
what we've really defined and
is a system of equations,
each of which is a line.
But it's a line if you draw the
axes as C and D.
Because the first one is, well,
it's a little cut off,
but it's 3C plus D equals 9.
It doesn't really look like it's
in y equals mx plus b form, but
you could rearrange it to be in
that form.
You could say D equals 9 minus
3C.
It's a little confusing here,
but the D is what you would
normally think of as y and y
equals mx plus b,
and the c is what you would
think of as x.
I'm not using x and y here
because that's what I call the
vectors.
So each line here,
like this one,
that corresponds to the blue
line.
This corresponds to the green
And so each component,
where we're dealing with vectors
in R3, so there are three
components,
defines a new line in the CD
space,
OK?
And the fact that all three of
these lines,
the first coming from the first
component of the vector, the
second coming from the second
component,
the third coming from the third
all three of these lines happen
to intersect at just one point.
And that point is where c equals
4 and d equals negative 3.
That's telling us the amount of
each vector we need to take of x
and y to make the output that we
wanted,
z.
And because all three of these
conditions,
you can think of all three
highlighted equations as
conditions that c and d must
satisfy,
because all three of these
conditions can be satisfied by a
combination of c and d, Well,
then it is possible to make z
using x and y.
Do we see how that's the case?
Now, from this picture,
hopefully it's not too crazy to
imagine drawing three lines that
don't all intersect at one
point.
It's possible to do that.
And if we check out the notes,
there's an example of what this
could look like.
So if I instead change the
vector that I think of as z, So
before we had 9, negative 16,
negative 1.
Now I have 9, negative 16, and 2
instead of negative 1.
That changes what the three
conditions that C and D need to
satisfy are.
The first two are the same
because the first two components
are the same.
The third is different.
Right, before we had 2C plus 3D
equals negative 1.
Now I'm changing that negative 1
to a 2,
just as an example.
And the resulting constraint
equations don't all intersect at
a single point.
It's possible to satisfy any
pair of these two,
because if you look here,
all pairs of lines intersect
somewhere, but they don't all
intersect at the same point.
So there's no values of c and d
that satisfy all three at the
same time,
which means there's no way to
make this vector b here using x
and y.
So in the first activity I gave
you, we kind of just got lucky.
I mean, it's not total luck.
I planted this because I knew
this would be the answer.
But we got lucky from the
perspective of, it was possible
to make the z using x and y.
But it doesn't always have to
be.
Do you see what I mean by that?
OK.
All right.
And this is a good example to
keep screenshotted in the iPad
notes.
Okay, so
the
final thing I want to do here
before we get into the truly new
idea for today is give you a
formal definition of what a
linear combination is.
I've given you several sort of
examples, but never the actual
definition
And this is what I alluded to on
Tuesday
So far we've used one variable
letter to be the placeholder for
the number of things in a vector
What was that number that we
what was that? What was that
variable? We talked about on
Tuesday that we will use for the
placeholder for the number of
things in a vector Yeah And but
now what I want to do is give
you a definition of linear
combinations That also has a
placeholder for the number of
vectors themselves
and That placeholder is going to
be the letter D
So I'm going to say suppose v1
v2 Dot-dot-dot through VD
Are all vectors in R n
So the English way to read this
is that we have D vectors
All with n components.
Anytime you see a
foreign-looking formula or
definition like this, the
easiest way to make sense of it
is to just make up numbers on
the side
and see if you can understand
what that's saying.
So what would it mean for d to
be equal to 5 and n to be equal
to 3?
Can someone tell me?
d equals 5, n equals 3.
What does that mean?
Yeah.
So it's like five vectors in
total, and each of them has
three, I guess, directions?
Exactly.
I have five vectors that all
live in R3.
So I could actually make a 3D
visual for you of these vectors.
But if I instead make it D
equals 3 and N equals 5,
well, now I have only three
vectors, but they live in R5, so
I can't drop for you.
So throughout this semester,
you're going to see lots of
definitions that involve N and
D.
And the way that I make sense of
them is to just make up values
for n and d and make sure I
understand the role of each of
those in the definition.
A linear combination
of these vectors,
of the v's, which I might call
the building blocks,
is any vector
that can be written
as
a1 times
v1 plus a2 times
v2 plus dot-dot-dot a,
d,
v,
where the a's
are all scalars.
This is really just a general
way of expressing the specific
examples we saw just now of like
4x minus 3y,
or 6u plus 1 half v.
Right there,
I just use the vectors x and y,
or u and v.
Here, I don't know how many
there are, so I'll probably run
out of letters before I,
you know, like I don't know how
many letters to use.
Which is why I just say, let's
just say there are d of them,
and call the vectors v1, v2,
dot, dot, dot, vd.
But notice,
the vectors have,
you know, the v's have arrow
hats on them, which means
they're vectors.
They're not the components of a
vector.
What does it mean that a1 to ad
are scalars? It just means those
are numbers rather than vectors.
So this is just the general
template for what a linear
combination looks like.
Any one specific linear
combination would have numbers
in it.
Like 3v1 plus 4v2 minus 7v3.
That's a linear combination of
v1, v2, and v3, for example.
Okay, this is just like the
general definition of a linear
combination
Okay questions so far
And I might and I'll note that
in a linear combination you will
call the A's the coefficients
But again the formulas look
scary all this is is just making
a new Lego out of of the amounts
of your building blocks you were
given.
The v's are the building blocks.
And this is saying,
let's just make something new by
taking some amount of each
building block.
Questions so far?
This is not our full coverage of
linear combinations.
This is just the beginning,
but linear combinations are
going to appear as a concept for
the rest of the semester.
So after today,
after this point in lecture,
for the rest of today and for
all of Tuesday, we're going to
talk about something else.
But then on Thursday, we're
going to come back to this idea
of linear combinations and
further explore what it really
meant for two vectors in R3 to
define a plane.
What does that mean?
And like what do five vectors in
R7 define?
Or what do a million vectors in
R2 define? Those are all things
that can be answered precisely.
And that's what we're gonna
start discussing.
But for now I want us to just be
familiar with the general idea
of a linear combination.
These are the kinds of pictures
to have in your mind.
Okay?
Right here I'm looking at
examples in R2,
but in the notes you can see
examples in R3 and it's
generally the same idea.
Taking a little bit of one
vector plus a little bit of
another plus a little bit of
another.
I say a little bit, it doesn't
have to be a small amount, it
can even be negative,
but that's the way you think of
it.
Using these building blocks to
produce a new vector.
Okay what questions do we have
so far?
Seem okay?
All right attendance time.
As a reminder Here,
you can find the form by going
to our course website, clicking
the attendance form.
It's 11.10.
We'll get started at 11.14.
So feel free to get some water,
take a break, stretch your legs.
Yeah,
come here, because I've got to
fix something.
It's probably too weird to
change.
I feel like I just can't.
Changing a profiler should sound
a bit different.
That means that those
coefficients can resolve.
Correct,
correct.
It means that there are a's that
would make the output vector
equal to a linear combination of
the inputs.
So like,
yeah, here,
this vector z can be written as
a linear combination of x and y,
but if you change this 1 to
something else, then it can't
be.
Well, because we already know
what values of c and d work in
the first two lines,
4 and negative 3,
which means that times 4, which
is 8,
plus that times negative 3,
which is negative 9, 8 minus 9,
or whatever.
I think that's supposed to be
negative.
That's the only number that
could be.
So if I change that to something
else, it couldn't be a linear
combination.
It's gonna take time, I can't do
it right now.
We're gonna talk more about
that.
This was just like an intuitive
introduction.
Thank you.
It's 11pm and then he said he's
hopping on a call right now and
it's 11.
Everyone checked in?
No, I'm checked in.
Yeah, I agree.
We need to get 11 p.m.
today.
We just held them at 11 a.m.
so I think it's an interesting
day.
Okay,
update 24 right now.
Okay, another two minutes.
I'm going to close the form.
Yeah, I just closed it.
Oh, you didn't check in?
Yeah, I got you.
OK,
try now.
Let me know once you do it, and
then I'll close it.
I didn't know this, but you can
look up the schedule of this.
I'm looking up the schedule of
the classroom that I left it in,
so I'm gonna go in between
there.
Just walk through the class.
I'm lecturing this.
It's 11.14
so let's keep going.
The next half of today's lecture
is not going to directly be
related to linear combinations
though they will still be
relevant.
For the next lecture and a half
we're gonna explore another
operation defined between two
vectors with the same number of
components.
So to recap, what are the things
we know how to do with vectors?
Well, if we have a vector,
first we can find its length.
We learned how to do that last
time.
If we have two vectors with the
same number of components, we
can add them.
We can also scale a vector by
any amount we want.
A negative scalar flips its
direction.
And if we take one or more
vectors,
scale each one by some amount,
and add the results, that's
called a linear combination.
The next operation I'm going to
introduce pushes,
you know, it sort of operates
outside of the framework of
addition and scalar
multiplication.
It does something different,
okay?
It's going to start with two
vectors, both in Rn,
and remember, this is just a
fancy way of saying we need to
assume they have the same number
of components.
And I know you saw the
definition in lab yesterday but
it's important enough that we
define it once again together.
Let's suppose my vector u has
the components
u1 through un and my vector v
has the components v1 v2 through
v in.
What I'm defining is a new
operation,
u dot v.
Notice this dot is in the
middle.
It's not like a decimal symbol.
And this operation is called the
dot product.
Not the product, the dot
product.
And here's how it's defined.
And what it's going to return is
the result of taking u1 and
multiplying it by v1.
Remember, here, u1 and v1, these
are just scalars.
Just to emphasize,
before we took a break,
the v1 and v2s we saw were
vectors.
They had vector hats written on
them, and those were
placeholders for vectors.
Now,
these v's are scalars,
different.
And so multiplying scalars,
we've been doing that since
kindergarten.
U1, V1.
Plus,
if you had to guess, what do you
think the next thing
after the pluses?
Yeah?
V2, V2? Yeah, I'm going to take
the second component of U and
multiply it by the second
component of V.
Do people learn how to multiply
in kindergarten?
I don't remember.
I don't know.
It's like a dance kindergarten.
Yeah, AP kindergarten.
All the way through UNVN.
So I'm going to do U1 V1 plus U2
V2 plus dot dot dot plus
UNVN.
So I'm going to take the first
of each,
multiply them.
Plus the second of each,
Plus the third of each, multiply
them, and so on.
Now, here's the most important
point I will make today.
The result that comes out of
this operation, and what type of
object is it?
Is it another vector?
It's a scalar.
OK, that's huge.
The way that my, I think I
mentioned before that I'm also
teaching a new math department
linear algebra class.
I talked about dot products
there last week.
And the way my co-instructor set
it to the class is he says,
think of the dot product as an
operation that eats two vectors
and spits out a scalar, OK?
I don't know if that will help
you remember it any better.
But the point here is that
unlike the sum of two vectors
which gave you a new vector,
here the dot product of two
vectors is giving you a number,
OK?
And what we're going to try and
understand today is what does
that number actually tell us
about the meaning of the vector?
Like sure, I can give you two
vectors, tell you to find the
dot product, it'll,
okay, two vectors have a dot
product of negative 30.
Who cares? Like what am I going
to do with that? That's what
we're going to try and
understand.
Okay,
before we get there,
what property does this dot
product, just from this
definition,
satisfy?
It's one that we talked about on
Tuesday as well for addition.
It's commutative.
Commutative.
Good.
Yeah,
it means u dot v is the same as
v dot u.
Okay.
So let's start by working out an
example.
I know you saw a few in lab
yesterday, but just to have one.
Let's suppose x is 4, 3,
y is negative 2, negative 5.
What is x dot y?
Well, Well,
I'm going to take the first
thing in x, multiply it by the
first thing in y.
That's going to be 4 times
negative 2.
Plus the second thing in x times
the second thing in y.
That's going to be 3 times
negative 5.
So the result is going to be
negative 8 minus 15, which is
negative 23.
So negative 23,
which is just a scalar,
is the dot product of x and y.
The question we have to answer
is, what does negative 23
actually tell us about x and y?
And it turns out it actually
means a lot.
It tells us something about the
geometry of x and y when you
draw them,
which is interesting because we
didn't draw them.
We're treating them as lists of
numbers, but the number negative
23 means something.
We're going to understand that
by the end of today.
OK.
Before we embark on our journey
of trying to understand what the
dot product actually tells us,
here's a question.
Is that a valid operation?
u.v.w?
No.
Why am I seeing a bunch of no's?
Like, why is that not legal?
Yeah.
So let's do the dot product.
You have a number, and so you
get a dot number.
Exactly.
The dot product is defined very
precisely as being an operation
that takes in two vectors and
returns a number.
If you want to multiply a vector
by a number,
that's legal also.
That's scalar multiplication,
but that's different than a dot
product.
And you wouldn't write this dot
here.
So my preference in this class,
whenever you're working out
algebra,
is to only use the dot symbol
when you're dealing with the dot
product of two vectors.
Even though it is perfectly
legal to say 3.4,
to say 3 times 4,
what I'd prefer is for you to
not do that, just so it's
crystal clear when you're
dealing with the dot product of
two vectors and when you're just
dealing with some other type of
multiplication.
So how would you write 3 times 4
instead?
You can just do 3 parentheses 4
or something.
Don't use the time symbol
because that's going to mean
something else too.
u.
OK,
so this is not defined.
If I wanted to somehow multiply
these three vectors,
u dot v times w,
that's a perfectly valid
operation.
u dot v gives me a number, and I
can multiply that
number by w.
And this will stretch or
compress w by whatever u dot v
is.
Similarly,
I could multiply u by v dot w.
This is a little strange because
I'm putting the scalar after the
vector, but that's fine.
That's fine, too.
Are these the same vector,
though?
No, because the first thing is a
scalar multiple of w.
The second thing is a scalar
multiple of u.
Unless v and u,
sorry,
unless w and u already pointed
in the same direction,
these are not going to point in
the same direction even.
So how could they be the same
vector?
So this is why I harped on, on
Tuesday,
the importance of being careful
with your notation here and very
clearly specifying what is a
vector and what is a number.
Because these operations are
defined very precisely.
Now let's try and understand
what the dot product actually
means and so to do that I'm
going to switch back to the
example vectors of X being four
three and Y
being you know I'm gonna
actually write these in colors
and
Y being negative two negative
five let's try and understand
what this actually tells us
about the relationship between x
and y.
x is going to be four units to
the right, three units up, let's
just say it's that.
And y is going to go left and
down,
right,
but mostly down.
And as we saw,
the dot product of x and y
was negative 23.
And so that must mean something,
or I'm claiming that means
something.
What I'd like to do is sort of
try and develop an intuitive
understanding of what it could
mean
by introducing another vector
and taking the dot product of
that other vector with x.
That other vector I want to
introduce, I'll say, is negative
6 comma 8.
Where is that going to look?
It's going to go left and up,
so something like that.
It's not drawn to scale,
but roughly you get the idea.
What is the dot product of x
with z?
Well, it's going to be 4 times
negative 6
plus what?
What's the dot product of x with
z?
What's the next factor?
Yeah, good.
3 times 8,
which is negative 24 plus 24.
Last I checked, that's equal to
0.
Okay,
so let's recap what we know so
far.
X and Y,
their drop product is negative.
And what do you notice about X
and Y, the arrows I've drawn for
them?
Yeah, they're pointing in almost
opposite directions.
It's not perfectly opposite
because they're not on the same
line, but they're almost
opposite.
Okay, and you can imagine what
if I took the dot product of x
with negative four, negative
three,
which is just the same as
negative x,
what would the dot product be?
it would be negative 25,
okay and that's a big negative
number and that would be the dot
product of X with a vector that
points in the exact opposite
direction of X.
What do you see about the dot
product of X with Z?
It's not a trick question.
What's it equal to?
Zero.
And what do you notice
geometrically about the
relationship with between X and
Z job indeed yeah it's
perpendicular okay
that is huge if the dot product
between two vectors
is zero
that means the vectors
are perpendicular.
Another fancy word for
perpendicular is orthogonal.
All it means is perpendicular.
It's the one we will use more in
this class and is more common to
use in machine learning.
All it means is perpendicular.
Now right now I haven't given
you a proof of why this is true.
This is just like proof by
vibes, trust me.
These two vectors have a right
angle and their dot product is
zero,
but what we're about to see is
that that's always true.
Anytime there's a right angle
the dot product is zero, and
there's a reason for that.
The weird thing is though we're
not always going to be able to
draw the vectors out.
Right here I pick vectors in R2
because they're easy to draw.
I could have given you an
example in R3, We could have
drawn those too.
What if we had two vectors in
R17?
They both have 17 components in
them.
How am I going to draw those?
I'm not.
But their dot product being 0 is
what we will use as the
definition of those vectors
being perpendicular to each
other.
It's sort of an abstract idea.
But this gives us a way of
defining what makes two vectors
perpendicular,
even if we can't visualize them.
They're perpendicular when their
dot product is 0.
Again, why is that the case?
We're going to see that shortly.
Finally, what happens if I get
the dot product of x with x?
The dot product of x with x.
What does that give me?
Yeah, it's on.
Good, it's just the length of x
squared.
Where is this coming from? Well,
x dot x should give me 4 times
4,
which is 4 squared, plus 3 times
3,
which is 3 squared.
But note, if I asked you find
the length of x, it would just
be the same thing that I wrote
with a square root,
right?
It would be the square root of 4
squared plus 3 squared.
So this is 25.
It is equal to the length of x
squared.
So that's an important fact.
There's nothing special about
this x here.
In general,
the length of a vector squared
is equal to the dot product of
the vector with itself.
Why would you need to know that?
Well, it's because there are
often proofs you need to do
involving the length of a
vector.
And the way you simplify things
is by writing the length of a
vector squared equals the dot
product of it with itself,
because then this allows you to
do a lot more algebra with it.
We're going to see a little bit
of that in just a moment.
OK, so what was the point of
this?
I wanted to give you some
understanding,
at least just by example for
now, that the dot product of two
vectors has something to do with
how closely aligned they are.
If they both point in similar
directions,
their dot product is big and
positive.
If they point in roughly
opposite directions, their dot
product is big and negative.
If they're at right angles with
each other,
their dot product is zero.
Do we see where that's coming
from?
Not where it's coming from, but
do we see at least in this
example that that's true?
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay,
so the key idea is that the dot
product
measures
similarity.
x dot y is
positive,
similar
directions,
zero, they're perpendicular.
I'll say large and positive
versus large and negative.
Because a dot product of 0.01
and a dot product of negative of
0.01.
Both of them are almost
indicative of vectors being
perpendicular.
I wouldn't say one is more
similar than the other.
OK,
now the question is, where does
this come from?
To see where it comes from,
and I'm going to move through
this a little quickly,
because it's not the main point.
What I want to do is just draw
two arbitrary vectors, both from
the origin,
u and v,
and I want to have a variable
that denotes the angle between
them, because it seems like the
dot product has some
relationship to the angle.
That's what was going on here.
Do we agree?
There's some connection.
So let's see if we can try and
make that connection precise.
What I'm going to do,
let me erase this axis line
here, I'm going to say the angle
between these vectors,
the angle between these vectors
is theta.
Here's a question for you.
So what is the name of that
vector I just drew?
The one that goes from the tip
of v to the tip of u.
How would I make that vector
using u and v?
Is that u plus v?
No, it's not.
u plus v would be like this plus
this.
It would live over here.
But what is it then?
Yeah?
3u minus v.
Close.
In fact, yeah, sorry.
I don't know why I said close.
Yeah, it is u minus v.
How'd you get that?
Because v plus dot vector would
make u,
so.
Good.
There's a few ways you can think
about it.
This is a vector we made by
taking v plus blank.
So if you say v plus blank
equals u, the blank is equal to
u minus v.
Another way of thinking about it
is how do you make this vector?
Well,
what you got to do is travel
opposite v,
that this is like a negative of
a v,
and then to dot add u.
So either way
you end up with u minus v.
So the reason I said close but
not so confidently that it was
true is because this is a tricky
idea even for me.
Is this u minus v or is it v
minus u?
Okay, when you're,
either way, it mostly looks the
same.
The question is where's the tip
of the arrow?
Right, if the tip was at the
bottom, well, then it would be v
minus u.
Okay,
but the way to see that this
vector is u minus v is that if
you took v and to that added
this thing we produced the v and
minus v would cancel out and
you're left with u.
Okay, so that's the vector u
minus v.
Okay.
Okay,
who remembers,
from high school,
a rule from trig that describes
the lengths of all three sides
of the triangle we're looking at
right now?
Gotta reach deep in the bag
here.
It's not SOHCAHTOA,
is it?
No, because SOHCAHTOA is more
about right-angle triangles and
none of the angles here
necessarily are right-angle.
Yeah?
Watch.
Law of cosines?
Yeah, the cosine law.
And what does that say?
The cosine law says,
if you have a triangle,
doesn't have to be right angle
triangle,
with sides length a,
b, and c,
and angles capital A,
capital B,
and capital C, using the
convention that angle C is
across side c,
angle A is across side What does
the cosine law tell you about
this set up?
Yeah?
c squared is equal to a squared
plus b squared minus
2 ab cosine of angle c.
Indeed.
The cosine law says c squared is
equal to a squared plus b
squared minus 2 ab cos c.
The thing is this is different
than a right angle triangle and
that there's no like
These labels are all arbitrary I
could have rewritten the
triangle with this being a this
being B and this being C and the
same thing would be true So like
another way you could think
about this
Is that a squared is equal to B
squared plus C squared minus 2 B
C
Cos a and it's also true that B
squared is equal to blah blah
blah.
Those are all true
You only really need to remember
one of them.
Probably didn't wake up thinking
you were going to have to
remember this today.
What does that have to do with
this situation?
How could we apply that here?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
We do the magnitude of u minus v
squared
Good is equal to the magnitude
of u squared plus the magnitude
of v squared plus 2 and the
magnitude of u and the magnitude
of v cosine theta.
Good.
All I'm doing is I'm saying c is
the length of u minus v.
Like this is the side length c,
this is the side length a,
this is the side length b, and
this is the angle c.
It's the same setup.
It's just that the definitions
involve vectors.
All right, so I got a length of
u squared plus a length of v
squared minus 2 length of u
length of
v cosine theta.
All right,
so we got a cosine theta.
So we have some relationship
between the lengths of the
vectors and the angle theta.
But the dot product does not
appear anywhere here.
So,
Remember, the whole point of
this was to try and understand
why it seems like the dot
product has something to do with
angle.
Based on this initial step,
your prediction probably has
something to do with the cosine
of the angle, but it's not clear
what the connection is.
So we've discovered.
One formula that relates the
length of u minus v squared to
the lengths of u and v and the
cosine of the angle between
them.
Question, how many people here
play Wordle still?
How many people played it today?
OK.
I probably just ruined it for
you.
Play it and then you'll see what
I meant.
What I need is another formula
that somehow relates or somehow
describes
the length of u minus v squared
that also involves a dot
product.
Because eventually, I want to
see the dot product equal
something something cosine
theta.
Because the whole point was to
see how the cosine of theta or
how theta is involved with the
dot product.
There's something we talked
about today that would allow us
to get there.
What can we do here? I want
another formula involving the
length of u minus v squared.
Caitlin? Didn't you say that
that would be equal to u
minus v u minus v? Excellent.
Yeah.
That's the important fact I
wanted you to remember.
If box is a vector,
it doesn't matter what it is.
It can be made up of operations
with other vectors.
the squared length of box is
equal to box dot product with
box.
That's true, even if the box is
made up as a linear combination
of other vectors and u minus v
indeed is a linear combination
of u and v.
So anything I can do to a vector
I can do to u minus v.
Now I'm gonna demonstrate some
of the properties that the dot
product satisfies.
One is that it has the
distributive property, which
means
you can distribute this dot
product as
As you would if these were all
scalars and this was regular
multiplication you could foil it
up
Foil being first outsides
insides law.
Okay.
So what would this expand out
to?
I Don't want to simplify yet.
I just want to write out all
four terms.
What are those terms gonna be?
How do we know if this is a dot
product or just a normal
multiplication?
It's because these are vectors.
There's no normal multiplication
between two vectors, like A
times B.
That's never a thing we discuss.
That's why I'm being very
precise with what type of
multiplication we're dealing
with.
There's scalar multiplication
which is number times vector and
then there's dot product which
is vector times vector but it
has to have this dot operation,
and the output is going to be a
number.
Just like the length of a vector
is a number,
you square the length of a
vector, that's also a number.
So the dot product of two
vectors is also a number.
Good.
But these are the right kinds of
questions to be asking.
If we expand this out, what are
we going to get?
What's the first of the four
terms we'd see?
u dot u.
Good, u dot u.
What's the next term we'd see?
Yeah.
u dot negative v.
Good.
You could say plus u dot
negative v.
What else would we have?
Go for it.
I thought you had your hand
raised.
Anyone else?
Yeah.
Negative v dot u.
And then lastly,
negative v dot negative v.
OK.
u dot u.
Is there anything I can simplify
that to?
Yeah.
u dot u is not it's not zero
remember zero is the dot product
of two vectors with a right
angle between them instead what
is it yeah yeah it's the squared
length of u that's the same
property we used to expand the
squared length of u minus v okay
now what do we have going on
here we have So u dot minus v
and minus v dot u.
This simplifies to minus 2 times
u dot v.
The minus factor in v can be
pulled out front.
So I could have written this as
minus u dot v minus v dot u,
and the dot product is
commutative.
So u dot v and v dot u are the
same thing.
So I have two of the dot
products.
And then what do I have at the
end?
I have the minus v dot minus v,
but I can pull out both factors
of negative 1.
That gives me minus 1 times
minus 1.
So this is a positive number.
And then I'm left with v dot v,
which is the same as the length
of v squared.
Alternatively, you could have
thought of this as the length of
negative v squared.
But negative v and v have the
same length.
So it's the same as the length
of v squared.
OK, what was the point of this
exercise?
And maybe just to make it even
more clear,
let's shuffle these things
around.
What do we see?
So going back to the original
expression,
you can take out u squared and v
squared like the magnitudes.
Yeah, also you dropped the
square there, but yeah.
Negative 2 u dot v is equal to
negative 2 u v cosine theta.
Exactly.
All we've done now is you've
come up with two ways of
describing the same thing.
That thing is the squared length
of u minus v.
The first way we did it
Involved the squared length of u
plus the squared length of v
minus 2 times the lengths of u
and v
Cos theta the second way mostly
looks the same but instead of
minus 2 length of u length of v
cos theta
We just have minus 2 u dot v
But these are the same thing
These are two ways of describing
the exact same quantity one way
I did it using the cosine law
the other I did it by using
properties of the dot product
So,
because these are equal,
if I set these both equal,
the length of u squared and v
squared cancel out.
Oops,
this should be yellow.
And so to be precise,
all of this is equal to all of
this.
Okay, so if I subtract the
squared length of u and the
squared length of v from both
sides, v from both sides,
and then divide both sides by
negative 2,
what am I left What am
I left with?
What am I left with? Same.
Yeah,
this tells me the dot product of
u and v
is equal to the length of u
times the length of v times the
cosine of the angle between
them.
So no wonder the dot product
seemed like it was related to
the angles between the vectors
is because it is.
It's the length of the first
times the length of the second
times the cosine of the angle
between them.
But this is not a different dot
product.
This is
equal to the same dot product we
saw before.
This new one that we found,
I might call the geometric
definition,
and this original one I might
call the algebraic definition.
Now you might say, well,
when would I ever know the angle
between two vectors?
The answer is you wouldn't
already know the angle.
What this allows you to do is
compute the angle between two
vectors, or at least the cosine
of the angle between two
vectors.
And what that gives us is a way
of measuring
how similar two vectors are even
when they're in higher than
R3,
or they have more than three
components.
All of these formulas work, even
if the vectors have 74 things in
them.
If you took your two vectors in
R74
and used the algebraic
definition to get their dot
product, and you found their
lengths as well,
well, then you could solve for
the cosine of the angle between
them.
And what is the cosine of an
angle?
What's the max and min that
could be?
Yeah,
great.
Negative 1 and 1.
Yeah, it's between negative 1
and 1.
If the cosine of an angle is 1,
that means the vectors point in
the exact same direction.
The theta between them is 0.
If they point in exact opposite
directions,
well then the theta is 180 and
the cosine of theta
is negative one.
That's why when they point in
opposite directions,
the dot product is negative.
And when they're perpendicular,
what's the cosine of 90 degrees?
Zero.
So all of that behavior is
coming from this equivalence.
The last thing I'll write here
is that if you write out u dot v
equals the length of u length of
v cos theta
You can solve for just the cos
theta, which is u dot v
over the length of u
Times the length of v and
sometimes this is called the
cosine
Similarity
And for the reasons we just
discussed, because the cosine of
an angle is between negative one
and one,
so is this.
And this gives us a way of
measuring the similarity of two
vectors with any number of
things in them.
So one of the cool applications
you'll see in next week's lab is
we show you how to convert
presidential State of the Union
speeches,
which are like the speech that
whoever's the president that
year gives in March, just like
talking about the world, I
guess.
You convert those to vectors,
and what we're going to do, and
you're going to write code for
this, is find the similarities
between all pairs of speeches.
You can look at over time,
like,
okay,
Joe Biden's last speech, whose
speech was that most similar to,
and whose speech was that least
similar to?
Of course, the thing it's most
similar to is Joe Biden's own
speech the year before, because
they used similar words,
but then you can see various
trends over time, and when
there's a speech near wartime,
like at the start of World War
I, it's very dissimilar because
they use lots of different
words, you can do all of that
using this cosine similarity
logic.
So we're going to show you some
of those examples
in coming up assignments.
OK,
I have ops stars after this,
like usual, and homework two is
due tomorrow.
It's sort of the last time I've
heard
it.
I feel like it makes a lot of
sense to rate it.
I'm like embarrassed to go sit
down and say, well I don't know,
I just want to make a plan.
It's like one where,
I don't know if he did 4B,
but there is like a video of A
and 4B and like, it's right up
there,
and then like,
that's probably like, a little
bit.
And then like, I don't know, I
think I better use the mic.
I would like to see it.
Already?
Yeah.
Here's like, how cool is this.
Like,
you guys are like, at the same
point.
I make,
like, some cannoli.
um...
I think
it's like starting like Sunday
is
when I think the last wave of
stuff that I thought I could do.
I think so, because for the
volume.
I have to study for e-cast and
make all the materials for that.
I have to like,
I think it should be.
I want to like,
there's something here I want
to,
we have everything but our
requirements that we
have.
We're changing our name from
Sproat to Sproat,
Please sit in your Tuesday
groups.
I mean you're kinda sitting
where you usually sit, I
believe,
but Tuesday please sit in those
groups.
We're here on Tuesday,
just find a group to attach to.
I don't know how to do
electrical.
I feel like I have a very easy
2,000-year-old problem.
Yeah, it took me like three
hours to do the 3D one.
I'm pretty bad about that.
Also,
I messed him across from him
like three times.
And then I messed up that one.
I think,
yeah, I know what you're talking
about.
I'm going to try to keep up with
you.
Wouldn't even finish.
Yeah, it just feels so wrong.
That's what I'm saying.
Like, I'll be chill.
I know what you're talking
about.
The answer's in the log.
It's like,
yeah.